<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Volume III. Inscriptions of Chersonesos and vicinity</title>
                <title xml:lang="ru">Том III. Надписи Херсонеса и окрестностей</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <group>
            <text xml:lang="en">
                <body>
                    <div>
                        <head>Igor Makarov</head>
                        <p>This is the first electronic edition of the inscriptions from Chersonesos and its vicinity, from the Northern Black Sea
                            (IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> vol. III). The introduction, editions and commentary are by Igor Makarov,
                        English translations are by Irene Polinskaya. The inscriptions were encoded following
                        the <ref target="http://epidoc.sf.net/">EpiDoc</ref> Guidelines for use of XML for ancient
                        documentary editions, and the website and supporting materials are the work of Gabriel Bodard,
                        Irene Polinskaya and colleagues at the Department of Digital Humanities, King's College London.</p>
                        
                        <div>
                            <head><ref target="introduction.html">Introduction</ref></head>
                            <p>[ENGLISH INTRO NEEDED]</p>
                            <!--<divGen type="intro-toc"/>-->
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head><ref target="/3/toc.html">Inscriptions</ref></head>
                            <p> [ANY COMMENT HERE ABOUT THE ORDERING OF THE INSCRIPTIONS, GIVEN THAT THE PE NUM ASSIGNMENT IS LARGELY RANDOM?], and also accessible
                                via the indices to the whole corpus and the search/browse interface.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <text xml:lang="ru">
                <body>
                    <div>
                        <head>Игорь Макаров</head>
                        <p>Первое электронное издание надписей Херсонеса и его окрестностей (IOSPE<hi rend="superscript">3</hi> III). Автор введения, надписей и комментариев Игорь Макаров. 
                            Английский перевод Ирины Полинской. Электронное издание следует руководящим принципам схемы EpiDoc, использующей платформу XML 
                            для публикации древних документальных источников. Сайт электронного издания и документация разработаны Габриэлем Бодар, 
                            Ириной Полинской и сотрудниками Факультета Цифровых Гуманитарных наук при Кингс Колледж Лондон.</p>
                        <div>
                            <head><ref target="introduction-ru.html">Введение</ref></head>
                            <p>[RUSSIAN TEXT NEEDED]</p>
                            <!--<divGen type="intro-toc-ru"/>-->
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head><ref target="/3/toc-ru.html">Надписи</ref></head>
                            <p>[RUSSIAN TEXT NEEDED]</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
        </group>
    </text>
</TEI>
