<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Volume I. Tyras and vicinity</title>
                <title xml:lang="ru">Том I. </title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <group>
            <text xml:lang="en">
                <body>
                    <div>
                        <head>Askold Ivantchik</head>
                        <p>This is the first electronic edition of the inscriptions from Tyras and
                            its vicinity, from the Northern Black Sea (IOSPE<hi rend="superscript"
                                >3</hi> vol. I). The introduction, editions and commentary are by
                            Askold Ivantchik, English translations are by Irene Polinskaya. The
                            inscriptions were encoded following the <ref
                                target="http://epidoc.sf.net/">EpiDoc</ref> Guidelines for use of
                            XML for ancient documentary editions, and the website and supporting
                            materials are the work of Gabriel Bodard, Irene Polinskaya and
                            colleagues at the Department of Digital Humanities, King's College
                            London.</p>

                        <div>
                            <!-- Holding note until final versions of everything are ready -->
                            <head>Note for users</head>
                            <p>The current edition is preliminary. Please note that an updated version 
                                will be released in 2019. We recommend the forthcoming edition of 2019 for citation purposes. 
                                With questions and comments on the current version, please contact the author and editors:  
                                ivantchik@u-bordeaux-montaigne.fr, irene.polinskaya@kcl.ac.uk</p>
                            <!--<head><ref target="introduction.html">Introduction</ref></head>
                            <p>[TEXT NEEDED]</p>-->
                            <!--<divGen type="intro-toc"/>-->
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head><ref target="/1/toc.html">Inscriptions</ref></head>
                            <p>The inscriptions in this volume are grouped by Category of Text, with relevant sub-categories, 
                                and within the latter, by Date, in chronological order. They are also accessible via <ref target="../../indices/index.html">Indices</ref>, Ins. 
                                # window and the <ref target="../../search/index.html">Search Corpus</ref> interface.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
            <text xml:lang="ru">
                <body>
                    <div>
                        <head>Аскольд Иванчик</head>
                        <p>Первое электронное издание надписей Тиры и ее окрестностей (IOSPE3 I).
                            Автор введения, надписей и комментариев Аскольд Иванчик. Английский
                            перевод Ирины Полинской. Электронное издание следует руководящим
                            принципам схемы EpiDoc, использующей платформу XML для публикации
                            древних документальных источников. Сайт электронного издания и
                            документация разработаны Габриэлем Бодар, Ириной Полинской и
                            сотрудниками Факультета цифровых гуманитарных наук при Кингс Колледж
                            Лондон.</p>
                        <div>
                            <!-- Holding note until final versions of everything are ready -->
                            <head>Вниманию пользователей</head>
                            <p>Текущая версия тома является предварительной. Дополненная и обновленная 
                                версия будет выпущена в 2019 и заменит текущую. Мы рекомендуем дождаться 
                                новой версии для использования в научных публикациях. С вопросами и замечаниями 
                                по текущей версии можно обратиться к автору и редакторам: 
                                ivantchik@u-bordeaux-montaigne.fr, irene.polinskaya@kcl.ac.uk</p>
                            <!--<head><ref target="introduction-ru.html">Введение</ref></head>
                            <p>[INTRODUCTION IN RUSSIAN]</p>-->
                            <!--<divGen type="intro-toc-ru"/>-->
                        </div>
                        <div>
                            <head><ref target="/1/toc-ru.html">Надписи</ref></head>
                            <p>Надписи корпуса сгруппированы по типам или жанрам; в типах надписей
                                выделяются подтипы. Те фрагменты надписей, жанровую принадлежность
                                которых определить не удалось, помещены в раздел Varia. Внутри
                                каждой группы надписи приводятся в хронологической
                                последовательности. Кроме этого, поиск можно осуществлять по
                                Указателям и через окошки « №" и "Поиск по корпусу."</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </body>
            </text>
        </group>
    </text>
</TEI>
