<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Byzantine 13: Building inscription of Isaak (?) (ed. A. Vinogradov)</title>
        <title xml:lang="ru">Византийская надпись 13: Строительная надпись Исаака (?) (редакция А. Виноградова)</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <group>
      <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
          <div>
          <head>Stone.</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Type of monument:</hi> Cornice. 
            <hi rend="italic">Material:</hi> Limestone. 
            <hi rend="italic">Description and condition:</hi> Re-used ancient cornice. Obverse side weathered.
            <hi rend="italic">Dimensions:</hi> H. 0.38, W. 0.49, Th. 0.24. 
            <hi rend="italic">Autopsy:</hi> non vidi.</p>
          <p>— <hi rend="italic">Find place:</hi> Chersonesos. 
            <hi rend="italic">Find circumstances:</hi> 1899, excavations of K.K. Kostsyushko-Valyuzhinich. 
            <hi rend="italic">Find context:</hi> Fortification walls, southern sector, inner face of wall.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Modern location:</hi> Unknown. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
          <head>Text field: </head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Faces code:</hi> f1. 
            <hi rend="italic">Style of lettering:</hi> Lapidary. Alpha with slanted crossbar, lambda with protruding left vertical,
              mu with curved hastae, nu with curved crossbar, sigma with serifs.
            <hi rend="italic">Letterheights:</hi> 0.02–0.03.</p>
          </div>
          <div>
          <head>Text:</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Origin of text:</hi> Chersonesos. 
            <hi rend="italic">Document type:</hi> Building inscription.  
            <hi rend="italic">Date:</hi> 1462 or 1472 CE. 
            <hi rend="italic">Dating criteria:</hi> Historical context.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Editions:</hi> L1. Kostsyushko-Valyuzhinich 1901, 40–41, № 2; 
          1.1. Vinogradov 2011a, 222–224, № 4.</p>
            
          <p>+ Ἀνεκε̣νίσθη ἐ̣[κ] β̣ά̣θρον<lb/>
            τὸ θεο]φ[ύλ]ακτον κέντ[ρον (pro κάστρον (?))<lb/>
            κ]αὶ ἕ̣τ[αι]ρ̣α̣ [ὀχυρώματα e.g.<lb/>
            τῆ̣[ς Χερσωνίας (?) ... μετὰ <lb/>
            κ]ὲ λοι[πῶν (?), ὑπὸ ἡμερῶν e.g. Ἰσαά-<lb/>
            κο̣υ̣ α[ὐ]θ[έν]τ&lt;ο&gt;υ [πόλεως Θ]ε-<lb/>
            ο[δώρους (καὶ) πα]ρ̣[αθαλασσίας, μη-<lb/>
            νὶ Μαρ]τ(ίου) α[ι’, ἰ]ν[δ(ικτιῶνος) ..´, ἔτους] ς̣[Ϡο´ resp. ς̣[Ϡπ´. <lb/>
            ...]M.</p>
          
          <p>Orig.: 6: Α.Θ..ΤΑΥ.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Apparatus criticus:</hi> 1–8: + Ἀνεκαινίσθη ... θεοφύλακτον (?) ... ὑψηλότατον (?) Latyshev.
            <figure><graphic url="13.jpg" width="400px" height="346px" rendition="float:right;"/></figure></p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Translation:</head>
            <p>Renovated from the foundations, the God-guarded citadel (?) and other fortifications (?) of Chersonia (?) ... 
              together with other (?), in the days of (?) Isaak the lord of the city Theodoron and of its coastline, 11th of March,
              in the ... indiction, year 6970 (or 6980) ...</p>
        </div>  
          
          <div>
            <head>Commentary:</head>
            <p>The article authored by Kostsyushko-Valozhinich but published on behalf of the editor (i.e. V.V. Latyshev)
              offered the reading of three words but noted that the inscription consisted of eight lines. The drawing of the inscritpion
              in Latyshev's archive, preserved in the St Petersburg branch of the Archive of the Russian Academy of Sciences
              (Ф. 110. Оп. 1. Д. 98. Л. 431), is not accompanied by a transcription. Descriptions of letter-forms are taken from this drawing.
              The inscription was found with no. 4.</p>
            <p>Line 1. In the formula "renovated from the foundations" the term ἀνεκενίσθη apparently indicates not consecration
              but a rebuilding from ruins of some citadel (see commentary to no. 169). </p>
            <p>Lines 2–5. The attribute "God-guarded" is reconstructed hypothetically. The term θεοφύλακτος (cf. Nos. 163, 168),
               in the region of the Northern Black Sea, is attested as a standard epithet of the city of Theodoron, and serves as the basis
               for attributing this inscription to Theodoron. The late Byzantine date of the inscription is suggested by the shape of the
               alpha with the slanted crossbar and upward extension of the right vertical, as well as by the nu with the S-shaped
               crossbar, for which there is a parallel in no. 214 (1427 CE).</p>
            <p>Lines 5–7.  The title of the ruler can be reconstructed from other 15th-century inscriptions from Theodoron.
              Judging by the remains of the letters he was Isaak (see commentary to no. 12, where the same name occurs).</p>
            <p>Line 8. At the end of the line stigma is clear: this can only signify a year. A sampi should have followed, after which
              there is enough space only for one more letter, signifying a decade. Because there is a great likelihood that the inscription
              was comissioned by Isaak of Mangup (see above), who ruled between 1459 and 1475, the missing letter could have been 
              either an omicron or a pi, which correspond to 6970 and 6980, from the creation of the world, i.e. 1462 and 1472 CE.</p>
        </div>
        </body>
      </text>
      
      
      <text xml:lang="ru">
        <body>
          <div>
          <head>Камень.</head>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Разновидность:</hi> Карниз. 
            <hi rend="italic">Материал:</hi> Известняк. 
            <hi rend="italic">Описание и состояние документа:</hi> Античный карниз во вторичном использовании. Лицевая сторона выветрена. 
            <hi rend="italic">Размеры:</hi> Высота 0,38; ширина 0,49; толщина 0,24. 
            <hi rend="italic">Автопсия:</hi> non vidi.</p>
          <p>— <hi rend="italic">Место находки:</hi> Херсонес. 
            <hi rend="italic">Условия находки:</hi> 1899 г., раскопки К.К. Костюшко-Валюжинича. 
            <hi rend="italic">Контекст находки:</hi> Оборонительные стены, южный участок, внутренняя сторона, пом. 25 и 26, кладка.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Место хранения:</hi> Неизвестно. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
          <head>Эпиграфическое поле:</head> 
           <p><hi rend="italic">Код фаса:</hi> f1. 
            <hi rend="italic">Стиль письма:</hi> Лапидарный. Альфа с наклонной поперечиной, лямбда с левым верхним выступом,
            мю прогнутое, ню с изогнутой поперечиной, сигма с апексами. 
            <hi rend="italic">Высота букв:</hi> 0,02–0,03.</p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Текст:</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Происхождение текста:</hi> Херсон. 
            <hi rend="italic">Характер документа:</hi> Строительная надпись.  
            <hi rend="italic">Датировка текста:</hi> 1462 или 1472 гг. 
            <hi rend="italic">Обоснование датировки:</hi> Исторический контекст.</p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Издания:</hi> L1. Косцюшко-Валюжинич 1901, 40–41, № 2; 
          1.1. Виноградов 2011a, 222–224, № 4.</p>
          
          <p>+ Ἀνεκε̣νίσθη ἐ̣[κ] β̣ά̣θρον<lb/>
            τὸ θεο]φ[ύλ]ακτον κέντ[ρον (pro κάστρον (?))<lb/>
            κ]αὶ ἕ̣τ[αι]ρ̣α̣ [ὀχυρώματα e.g.<lb/>
            τῆ̣[ς Χερσωνίας (?) ... μετὰ <lb/>
            κ]ὲ λοι[πῶν (?), ὑπὸ ἡμερῶν e.g. Ἰσαά-<lb/>
            κο̣υ̣ α[ὐ]θ[έν]τ&lt;ο&gt;υ [πόλεως Θ]ε-<lb/>
            ο[δώρους (καὶ) πα]ρ̣[αθαλασσίας, μη-<lb/>
            νὶ Μαρ]τ(ίου) α[ι’, ἰ]ν[δ(ικτιῶνος) ..´, ἔτους] ς̣[Ϡο´ resp. ς̣[Ϡπ´. <lb/>
            ...]M.</p>
          
          <p>Orig.: 6: Α.Θ..ΤΑΥ.</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Критич. аппарат:</hi> 1–8: + Ἀνεκαινίσθη ... θεοφύλακτον (?) ... ὑψηλότατον (?) Latyshev.
              <figure><graphic url="13.jpg" width="400px" height="346px" rendition="float:right;"/></figure></p>
          </div>
          <div>
          <head>Перевод:</head>
          <p>Обновлена от оснований [бого]х[ра]нимая креп[ость (?)] и другие [укрепления (?) Херсонии (?) … вместе] c про[чими (?), во дни (?) Исаа]ка, властителя [города] Ф]ео[доро и п]о[морья, 1]1 [ма]р[та, в .. и]н[дикт, в] 6[970] (или: 6[980]) году…</p>
          </div>
          <div>
          <head>Комментарий:</head>
          <p>В статье Косцюшко-Валюжинича от имени редакции (т.е. В. В. Латышева) дано лишь чтение трех слов и указано, что в надписи было 8 строк. Рисунок надписи из архива Латышева хранится в ПФА РАН (Ф. 110. Оп. 1. Д. 98. Л. 431) без чтения. Из него взяты сведения о шрифте. Надпись найдена рядом с № 4.</p>
          <p>1. В формуле «обновлен от оснований» следует «обновлением» следует понимать, по всей видимости, не «освящение», а восстановление из руин какой-то крепости (см. комм. к № 169).</p>
          <p>2–5. Описание ее реконструируется предположительно. Термин «богохранимый» (ср. № 163, 168), являющийся в Северном Причерноморье устойчивым эпитетом Феодоро, заставляет связать данную надпись именно с Феодоро. В ее поздневизантийской датировке убеждают формы альфы с наклонной перекладиной и дополнительным верхним штрихом и ню с S-образной диагональю, находящие параллели лишь в № 214 (1427 г.)</p>
          <p>5–7. Титулатура правителя восстанавливается легко по другим феодоритским надписям XV в. — судя по остаткам имени, им был Исаак (см. комм. к № 12). В пользу этого говорит и наличие такого имени в № 12.</p>
          <p>8. В конце строки читается стигма: это может быть только часть обозначения года. За стигмой должна была следовать сампи, после которой в строке остается место максимум для одной буквы, обозначавшей десятки. Поскольку с большой долей вероятности надпись была поставлена Исааком Мангупским (см. выше), правившим между 1459 и 1475 гг., то этими буквами могут быть только омикрон или пи, которые дают соответственно 6970 и 6980 гг. от сотворения мира, т.е. 1462 и 1472 гг. по Р.Х.</p>
        </div>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>
  </text>
</TEI>
