<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
  xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:lang="en">Digital Epigraphy</title>
        <title xml:lang="ru">Электронная публикация эпиграфических надписей</title>
        <title xml:lang="uk"></title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Publication Information</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Information about the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <group>
      <text xml:lang="en"><body>
        <p>The EpiDoc Guidelines, recommendations for XML mark-up of epigraphic documents, were
          originally conceived in 2000, by Tom Elliott, then director of the Ancient World Mapping
          Center at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, with Hugh Cayless and Amy
          Hawkins. The guidelines and other tools have matured considerably through extensive
          discussion in online fora such as the Markup list, at several conferences, and through the
          experience of various pilot projects.2 The first major—but not by any means the
          only—epigraphic project to adopt and pilot the EpiDoc recommendations has been
          Inscriptions of Aphrodisias , and the guidelines have reached a degree of stability for
          the first time during this process.</p>
        <p>EpiDoc specifies the use of XML (Extensible Markup Language), an industry standard
          maintained and documented by the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C 1996-2007). In simple
          terms XML is a grammar for defining markup languages—including HTML, the principle
          language of the Web. XML is a software- and platform-independent language, optimised for
          compatibility, interchange, and durability, which means that it is ideal for archive
          storage as well as web and database publication. Since XML, and, now less commonly, its
          parent language SGML, are used almost universally for encoding and storing data in the
          commercial sector by computer professionals, publishers, analysts, archivists, economists
          and so forth, advantages over a proprietary database system are increasingly clear. In
          particular, it is likely that any changes in technology that require upgrades to either
          the encoding of XML itself, or its transformation and delivery, will be handled by those
          with the resources to do so, and that academic projects can coat-tail on this progress,
          rather than having to invest in expensive solutions themselves or see their materials fall
          out of date.</p>
        <p>An essential concept behind EpiDoc is the understanding that this form of semantic markup
          is not meant to replace traditional epigraphic transcription based on the Leiden
          conventions. The XML may (and almost inevitably will) encode more information than the
          range of brackets and sigla used in Leiden, but there will always be a one-to-one
          equivalence between Leiden codes and markup features in the EpiDoc guidelines. This means
          that, at a minimum, a text encoded in Leiden can be marked up using EpiDoc XML with very
          little extra editorial intervention—and in fact tools exist whereby this process can be
          automated to 95% or better. </p>
        <p> An EpiDoc file is a representation in XML of the edition of one inscription or a group
          of inscriptions. At a minimum the file will contain a text in Greek or Latin, probably
          with editorial sigla. It may also contain apparatus, translation, commentary, description
          and dating of the text or object, history of the inscription, bibliography, or any other
          information that is normally published in a scholarly edition. The file may also contain
          cross references to other texts, files, indices, tables, appendices, and images. </p>
        <p> An inscription or corpus of inscriptions marked up in EpiDoc XML may be rendered for
          display or publication in a variety of forms; indexed, processed, queried and searched
          like a database, but on any computer and in one of countless available search programmes;
          interchanged with other projects, scholars, software, and encoding systems. </p>
        <p> As well as offering a choice of rendering styles, this semantic markup allows us to
          perform intelligent processes and searches upon the marked-up text. We can perform a word
          search only for certain words when they are complete and not made up in part or in full by
          editorial supplements, for example. Certain types of damage may be significant in their
          own right, such as erasure, which might represent damnatio memoriae, or the replacement of
          one name or expression with another.</p></body>
      </text>
      <text xml:lang="ru"><body>
        <p>в разработке</p></body>
      </text>
      
      <text xml:lang="uk">
        <body>
          <p></p>
          <p></p>
          <p></p>
          <p></p>
          <p></p>
          <p></p>        
      </body>
      </text>
    </group>
  </text>
</TEI>
